BU Records: Armed Services Representative, Inclusive: 1942-1945, undated, Bulk: 1943-1944
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Armed Services Representative
Inclusive: 1942-1945, undated, Bulk: 1943-1944
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/12
Duncan, Elma Merle Mears McClellan, 1895 - 1985
2 document boxes.
This collection consists of correspondence sent by former students, parents, and government officials to Merle Mears McClellan, Baylor University's Armed Services Representative during World War II.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Elma Merle Mears, the donor of this collection, was born on 1895 September 6 to Thomas Robert Mears and Rosa Elma Belcher Watkins. Her family moved to Gatesville when her father was elected to the Texas House of Representatives. Merle, who preferred to be called by her middle name, graduated from the University of Texas in 1917 with a double major of history and science. Over the next few years, she served as a teacher in the Gatesville area.
On 1920 June 1 Merle married a lawyer named William Clay McClellan. In 1922, the couple had their only child, a son named Thomas Rufus McClellan. The McClellan family moved to Waco to further Clay’s law career, but in 1938, he passed away from cancer at the age of 48. The following year, Thomas accepted an appointment to the U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis, Maryland. Merle accompanied her son and subsequently began graduate work at George Washington University.
Merle eventually returned to Waco where she earned a Master’s degree in history at Baylor University in 1941. She taught briefly at Baylor (1941-1945) while also serving as the Armed Services Representative for the university. Baylor President Pat Neff appointed Merle to the position in the spring of 1943. Her responsibilities centered on acting as a liaison between the government and the university, particularly proposing exemptions from military service on a case-by-case basis.
Merle left Baylor in 1945 when she married a businessman named Bruce Duncan. She eventually taught a second stint at Baylor University (1956-1960) before retiring in Waco. She passed away on 1985 September 30 at the age of 90.
Scope and Content
This collection houses correspondence written to Merle McClellan who served as Baylor University’s Armed Services Representative in 1943. While the inclusive dates represented in the collection range from 1942 to 1945, most of the letters were written between 1943 and 1944.
The United States government initiated the Army Specialized Training Program and the V-12 Navy College Training Program in 1943. In an effort to develop educated and well-rounded military officers, the U.S. War Department worked in cooperation with colleges and universities across the nation to create an appropriate curriculum. After persistent negotiations by Baylor University President Pat Neff, Baylor was approved as a training site on 1943 April 1. Neff appointed Merle McClellan as the acting liaison between the university and the military. The training programs ultimately ended in 1944, however, with the Allied invasion of Europe. The military needed all available men and women for the offensive.
Series I. Correspondence is the only series in the collection. Most of the letters were penned by Baylor students after they had moved on to other universities for further training or had been deployed overseas. Merle also received letters from her students’ parents, Texas Representative Bob Poage, Texas Senator Tom Connally, and various officers in the U.S. military involved in oversight of these training programs.
Arrangement
The correspondence within this collection was arranged alphabetically by last name prior to this latest round of processing. Many of the folders had incomplete titles, and most lacked inclusive date ranges. There were no previous finding aids or inventories available.
The original order of the collection has been maintained. The materials are now arranged into a single series, I. Correspondence.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/12. Acquired 1977-08-00
Related Resources
Items in related collections
BU Records: Army Specialized Training Program, Inclusive: 1943-1944, undated
Related references
BU Records: Armed Services Representative, Accession #BU/12, Box #1, Folder #30, The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
Campbell, Randolph B. “Duncan, Elma Merle Mears McClellan.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2017 December 4.
Interview of Merle Mears McClellan Duncan by Janelle Easley. Oral History of the Woman in Waco, January 12-14, 1977. Transcript, Baylor University Institute for Oral History, Waco, Texas.
Madsen, Sarah. “The Impact of World War II on Baylor University’s Course and Program Offerings.” HESA Baylor History Project. Accessed 2017 December 4.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Poage, W. R. (William Robert), 1899-1987 -- Correspondence.
Subjects (Organizations)
Army Specialized Training Program (U.S.) -- Records and correspondence.; Baylor University -- Students -- Correspondence.; Connally, Tom, 1877-1963 -- Correspondence.; Navy V-12 Program (U.S.) -- Records and correspondence.; United States. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence.; United States. Army -- Officers -- Training of -- Texas -- Waco.; United States. Navy -- Officers -- Correspondence.; United States. Navy -- Officers -- Training of -- Texas -- Waco.
Subjects
Military education -- Texas -- Waco.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Correspondence, 1942-1945, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Series I. Correspondence is the only series found in the collection. It consists of letters sent to Merle Mears McClellan, the Armed Services Representative for Baylor University during World War II. Her correspondents were primarily former Baylor students who had since been transferred elsewhere in the United States for further training or had been deployed to combat overseas. There are also a few letters from parents of such students along with letters from Texas Congressmen and various military officials. Overall, the materials are in good condition.
  - Alewine, Ralph, 1943 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appel, Carl L., 1944 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bailey, Weldon K., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Baldwin, James, 1943 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ball, Horace, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barbour, Gene, 1943 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barton, Alton W., 1944 March 11-April 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bergeson, Eldridge G., 1943 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bierborner, William "Bill" H., 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Blodgett, Mr. and Mrs. N.S., 1943 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Blodgett, W. Terrell, 1943 April-August (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Blodgett, W. Terrell, 1943 September-1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Boyd, Ernest, 1943 May-1944 July (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bramlette, William Howard, 1943 June-July (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bright, Robert E., 1943 February (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Burton, L. Gayle, 1943 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Carter, Douglas, 1943 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clark, Norris, 1943 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cole, Frank Keith, 1943 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Coleman, George, 1943 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Collier, Billy, 1943 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Connally, Tom: U.S. Senate, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cook, Jr., G.W., 1943 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Corrie, Walter S., 1943 May (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Darnell, Billie Cole, 1943 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Davidson, Shirl Dean, 1943 May-1944 June (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Davis, Bill, 1943 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Davis, Lacy, 1943 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Donohoe, Henry T., 1944 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Duncan, Mrs. J. Bruce, 1945 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Duncan, Jr., William "Bill", 1943 May-1944 January (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - England, Mrs. Nick, 1943 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Ferguson, Dorothy Jean "Mrs. Roy J.", 1944 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Fletcher, Douglas, 1943 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Fox, Marjorie G. "Mrs. John H.", 1943 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Garrett, Vernon, 1943 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Gassnir, Samuel Horner, 1943 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hames, Lamar, 1943 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hamilton, Charles S., 1944 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Haralson, Keith D., 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Harrell, L.E., 1943 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Harris, Marion M., 1943 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hazpenstein, Archie A., 1943 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Holt, John M., 1943 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Hoovestol, Joel, 1944 March-April (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Howard, James H., 1943 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Howard, Louis Allan, 1944 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Hudson, Douglas, 1943 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Hugghins, John, 1943 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Humble, Mrs. O.P., 1943 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Iles, Jimmy, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Jackson, Bessie Earle, 1943 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Jacobs, Randall: Joint Army and Navy Personnel Board, 1943 July 8 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jennings, Kenneth, 1943 July 20 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Johnson, Richard W., 1943 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Johnson, Jr., Tom, 1943 June 28 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Jones, Otto Jarold, 1943 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kinard, Dwight L., 1943 June-September (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Koppman, Lionel, 1943 June 9 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lawrence, Roderick Quentin, 1943 June 13 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lumpkin, Gilbert Horace, 1943 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - MacSmith, John, 1943 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - McClellan, T.R.: Time Magazine, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - McCommon, Howard, 1943 March 11 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - McFarlane, D.J.: Joint Army-Navy-Marine Corps-Coast Guard College Procurement Committee, 1943 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - McGregor, Charles B., 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - McLendon, Will "Billy" L., 1943 June 13 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Moore, P.L., 1943 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Nalley, Fred: Excerpt, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Nelson, Edward W., 1943 May 26 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Nelson, Travis, 1943 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Nokes, Jr., George O., 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Paxton, James Robert, 1943 June 18 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Phillips, Wendell I., 1943 June 10 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Poage, W.R.: U.S. House of Representatives, 1943 June 4 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Pope, William "Bill", 1943 July-1944 January (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Priolo, Roy, 1943 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Pritchett, Lawson, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Quay, John E., undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Quement, F.J., 1942 August 19 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Raynor, Frank L., 1943 June 13 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Robinson, F.A., 1943 July-November (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Rose, George J., 1944 December 20 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Rouk, Jan, 1943 June 6 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Russell, Rudolph, 1943 July 11 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Saye, Jack E., 1944 August 16 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Score, J.N.R., 1943 June 21 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Seay, Frank Oliver, 1943 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Smith, George Byron, 1943 October 3 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Smith, Jay King, 1943 September 9 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Smith, Vernon L., 1943 May-October (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Strength, Jack and Gladys, 1943 February-October (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Stuart, Hal, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Thomason, John H., 1943 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Wade, Nelsyn Ernest Brooks, 1943 July 4 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Wallis, Gordon, 1943 May 24-June 7 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Ward, Jr., Robert L., 1944 April 6 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Wellborn, Charles (1 of 3), 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Wellborn, Charles (2 of 3), 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Wellborn, Charles (3 of 3), 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Wilkins, Thomas O., 1945 May 26 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Williams, Charles F., 1943 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Williams, Mrs. Bryan, 1943 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Williams, Jr., Peeler, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - First Names Only, 1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)